<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://esteemed.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://esteemed.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-10-18T17:34:15+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Esteemed.io</title><subtitle>Scale your business with speed and confidence with trusted colleagues from the Esteemed Talent Network. Made up of over 13,000 digital professionals. The first and only integrated staffing and collaboration solution delivered through your existing communications platforms.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Three Cs for Landing a More Fulfilling Job</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/03/16/the-three-cs-for-landing-a-more-fulfilling-job/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Three Cs for Landing a More Fulfilling Job" /><published>2021-03-16T19:13:19+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-16T19:13:19+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/03/16/the-three-cs-for-landing-a-more-fulfilling-job</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/03/16/the-three-cs-for-landing-a-more-fulfilling-job/"><![CDATA[<p>The modern job search is a challenging one. Demand for many open positions outpaces supply, and for those seeking employment, job <em>fulfillment</em> is a critical piece to factor in. Whether you seek a pay increase, career advancement, or a fresh start, your job search requires patience. While online applications have made the job search easier, the number of applicants has skyrocketed, and data shows that only<a href="https://careers.workopolis.com/advice/only-2-of-applicants-actually-get-interviews-heres-how-to-be-one-of-them/"> 2 percent of applicants actually get interviews</a>. You simply cannot expect recruiters and hiring managers to respond to every inquiry.</p>

<p>What makes a candidate successful? It comes down to mindset. While some people dread the job search experience, others embrace the challenge. We all experience anxiety and frustration when the stakes are high and the uncertainty is higher. Simply knowing that you are not alone — that this is a normal response to an important life change — might allow you to adjust your mindset and normalize the fear.</p>

<p>In the 1970s, psychologist and author Suzanne Kobasa researched what she called “stress hardiness.” She studied executives at Bell Labs to better understand what made some people more resistant to stress than others. Those executives didn’t eschew stress; they befriended their stress by responding in a more positive manner to stressful events. Kobasa discovered three attitudes about stress and resilience (the Three Cs), and her findings can be applied to modern job searches. By employing a proper mindset and embracing pressure, you’re well on your way to landing a more fulfilling job.</p>

<h3 id="the-three-cs">The Three Cs</h3>

<h4 id="challenge"><strong>Challenge</strong></h4>

<p>Challenge is the first step to changing from a<a href="https://www.brainpickings.org/2014/01/29/carol-dweck-mindset/"> fixed mindset to a growth mindset</a>. Rather than viewing challenges as threats to the status quo, stress hardy individuals see challenges as opportunities for growth and learning. This strategy opens your mind to creative thought and boosts your motivation.</p>

<p>Begin your search by engaging in a period of self-discovery to appreciate who you are and what you are grateful for in your life. Look deeply at your professional and personal successes to build confidence and trust in what you know about yourself. You may want to journal about the types of positions that interest you, and why you are qualified for those positions. You can revisit your writings when you have a bout of imposter syndrome.</p>

<p>Use your insights to update your resume so that it better reflects your achievements and growth. “Your resume is ultimately your unique story of professional experience,” argues <a href="https://money.usnews.com/money/blogs/outside-voices-careers/2015/08/19/5-things-your-resume-is-not">Arnie Fertig</a>, founder of a career coaching organization. “[A proper resume includes] challenges, what you did and what you attained. It tells the story of a discrete set of work activities, the skills you’ve attained and the education and credentials that enable you to perform as a valued employee.”</p>

<p>When you change the lens through which you see your situation, you may find more positive and motivating ways to manage your job search. Embracing a growth mindset adjusts your perspective on failure by seeing challenges as opportunities to learn.</p>

<h4 id="commitment"><strong>Commitment</strong></h4>

<p>Commitment is feeling connected to your sense of purpose, and is closely aligned with values. Examining your values will help you to find fulfillment in your new position. If this is difficult for you, start by listing three to five people you admire. Then write down the traits of those people that resonate with you. You will begin to notice patterns that will reveal your values.</p>

<p>By keeping your values at top of mind, you can be more intentional about the positions you apply for, ensuring that your next opportunity will align with your needs. If a job description triggers an emotion, take a moment to notice how you feel. Are you triggered because you don’t feel smart enough, or are you empowered because the position might lead to a new growth opportunity?</p>

<p>Find meaning in your job search by taking an active approach. Take the time to find a job that aligns with your goals and values. This will keep you focused and engaged, even if faced with temporary setbacks.</p>

<h4 id="control"><strong>Control</strong></h4>

<p>Whether you view life as something to control or something that controls you, either way the outcome is added stress. Accepting what you cannot control and taking action on what you can keeps you from dwelling on the “should haves” and the “what ifs.”</p>

<p>The “should haves” are those regrets that arise from a past event. For example, if you aren’t offered the job, you might assume that you “should have” answered an interview question differently. But that might not have been the reason you weren’t hired. Rather than beating yourself up over your hindsight, recognize that there may be other explanations out of your control. Then you can begin to learn from the experience and accept the situation.</p>

<p>The “what ifs” are the narratives in your head about the future. “What if” I don’t get the job? “What if” they don’t like me? Catastrophizing the possibilities is exhausting. When we agonize over the uncertainty of the future, we become anxious and demoralized.</p>

<p>Recognize which aspects of the job search you have control over, and seek balance in how you control your situation. Plan, practice, reflect, ask for referrals, and be patient. Accepting that you are in an uncertain situation gives you space to befriend yourself with kindness.</p>

<h3 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>

<p>When you see resiliency as your ability to cultivate a more productive attitude towards stress, you are less likely to be driven by emotional reactivity. Here are some final tips for applying the Three Cs to your self-aware job search.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Adjust your expectations. Recruiters and hiring managers are busy. They may not get to your application. It isn’t necessarily about you.</li>
  <li>Be prepared. When you come into an interview prepared to tell your story, you will be perceived as authentic. Practice your pitch and responses to questions. Begin a meditation, breathing, or movement practice to calm your nervous system.</li>
  <li>Be on time. Rushing keeps us from experiencing that moment of present connection. Whether interviewing online or in-person, arrive early, feel your feet on the floor, and take a few deep breaths for grounding in the present moment.</li>
  <li>Engage in listening. During the interview, focus on the questions and not your response. Active listening keeps you in the present moment so that your mind doesn’t wander off. Managers are trying to assess your problem-solving skills; not make you feel incompetent. Rather than allowing feelings of self-judgment to arise if you don’t know the answer to a question, be honest when you reach the end of your knowledge.</li>
  <li>Cultivate kindness. Always extend a thank-you message after the interview, connect on LinkedIn, and follow up on next steps. Build a relationship by engaging. If you want others to value your worth, return them the same courtesy.</li>
  <li>Rejection hurts. If you don’t do well during the interview or if you fail to get the job, recognize that you don’t know with whom you competed and what value they brought to the table. Your self-worth is not tied to getting the job. Review your resume and interview, noticing whether there are things you could do better next time, and accept the outcome.</li>
</ul>

<p>A job search deeply tests our ability to be resilient. Practicing self-awareness — authenticity, non-judgment, acceptance, self-compassion — puts you in a position to reframe your job search as a learning opportunity. If you still find yourself highly stressed, recognize when you need outside support. Stay healthy by connecting with friends and getting enough sleep, good nutrition, and exercise. While not everyone may see your value, you can be confident in your own self-worth. Your next opportunity is right around the corner.</p>]]></content><author><name>Dori Kelner</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The modern job search is a challenging one. Demand for many open positions outpaces supply, and for those seeking employment, job fulfillment is a critical piece to factor in. Whether you seek a pay increase, career advancement, or a fresh start, your job search requires patience.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-daria-shevtsova-3626744.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-daria-shevtsova-3626744.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Software Development Trends for 2021</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/02/16/software-development-trends-for-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Software Development Trends for 2021" /><published>2021-02-16T20:48:41+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-16T20:48:41+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/02/16/software-development-trends-for-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/02/16/software-development-trends-for-2021/"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the pandemic, we’ve witnessed industries fast-tracking their digital transformation to simply stay afloat. As a result, the <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/30/why-demand-for-tech-talent-is-so-high/" target="_blank">demand for top tech talent</a> has never been higher.</p>

<p>The confluence of economic and work-life upheaval has changed the course of many of our lives. And the IT modernization tsunami has brought disruption on a massive scale.</p>

<p>Businesses are also banking on staying up-to-date and reliable during these challenging times. And as they scale back new projects they’ve shifted focus to core infrastructure, remote workflows, and cybersecurity sectors.</p>

<p>But the future looks bright for developers with the skills and flexibility to take advantage of this time of change and innovation. Here are some of the bigger trends taking center stage in 2021 and beyond.</p>

<h3 id="low-code-no-code">Low-code, No-code</h3>

<p>Low-code no-code (LCNC) solutions seem inescapable as they become more accessible and popular for scaling products quickly. For less tech-savvy teams they can bridge the gap with user-friendly, cross-platform UI, and let devs focus more on driving business.</p>

<p>“Because of its advantages, Gartner estimates that the low-code approach will account for 65% of all application development activity by 2024.” — What developers should look out for in 2021</p>

<p>And that doesn’t mean that developers will become obsolete … it means that hybrid teams will be able to orchestrate more, faster. Good business all around.</p>

<p>“Expect to see new hybrid teams emerge, with business users and professional developers building apps together with low-code tools built on cloud-native platforms.” — <a href="https://go.forrester.com/blogs/predictions-2021-software-developers-face-mounting-pressure/" target="_blank">Jeffrey Hammond</a>, VP &amp; Principal Analyst at Forrester Research</p>

<h3 id="edge--cloud-computing-decentralized-infrastructure">Edge + cloud computing: Decentralized infrastructure</h3>

<p>As data storage needs and management become a larger priority, businesses are looking to models that will save money and increase uptime. In the face of adversity, flexible options that solve these issues look promising for developers.</p>

<p>“Demand for cloud-native development skills is expected to expand in future years to satisfy the increased agility needed by organizations with a development model that span data centers and multi-cloud environments,” — <a href="https://www.techrepublic.com/article/developers-these-are-the-top-skills-you-will-need-in-2021/" target="_blank">Erica Langhi</a>, senior solution architect EMEA Red Hat</p>

<p>Edge computing also offers advantages that the cloud can’t solve on its own. And IT pros willing to wade in will see a lot of opportunities.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The worldwide Edge computing market is predicted to increase from 1.47 billion USD in 2018 to 26.84 billion USD by 2025.” — <a href="https://medium.com/better-programming/software-developer-trends-of-2020-and-beyond-d1b955bc46b8" target="_blank">Statista Research Department</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>As modernization costs create a need for many businesses to decouple compute from storage,</p>

<p>a greater reliance on hybrid cloud architectures will arise. This increases the demand for developers with the know-how to create apps built just for these use cases.</p>

<h3 id="the-rise-of-ai-and-ml">The rise of AI and ML</h3>

<p>The proliferation of artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning (ML) for transforming the user and customer experience is also sweeping industries. Some forecasts see AI-related business hitting $3.9 trillion by 2022.</p>

<p>Chatbots can now integrate AI to answer a client’s needs quickly and with a personal touch. And ML is helping test professionals enhance the efficacy of test automation by leaps and bounds.</p>

<p>As businesses ask developers to speed up this transformation and automation, developers with expertise in these fields are seeing a spike in demand. Not to mention cybersecurity (see: below) as AI is also being used to prevent and repel threats to keep businesses safe.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Demand for AI and Machine Learning skills is growing at a 71% compound annual growth rate through 2025 …. IT Automation job skills are predicted to grow 59% over the next five years.” — <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/louiscolumbus/2021/12/27/top-10-tech-job-skills-predicted-to-grow-the-fastest-in-2021/" target="_blank">Top 10 Tech Job Skills Predicted To Grow The Fastest In 2021</a></p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="serverless-and-kubernetes">Serverless and Kubernetes</h2>

<p>The flexibility and cost-effectiveness of Serverless infrastructures has grown by leaps and bounds (see also: cloud). Combined with the rising popularity of open-source, extensible platforms for managing storage and containerized services, there’s been a sea change for DevOps.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Serverless delivers exact units of resources in response to a demand from the application. … With traditional cloud computing, the computer resources are dedicated to you whether you’re using them or not while with Serverless, you’re dynamically pulling only what you need from a vast ocean of resources.” — <a href="https://dis.co/blog/serverless-computing-vs-cloud-computing-whats-the-difference/" target="_blank">What’s the Difference Between Cloud Computing and Serverless?</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>As workloads shift to highly adaptable platforms like <a href="https://enterprisersproject.com/article/2017/10/how-explain-kubernetes-plain-english" target="_blank">Kubernetes</a>, demand for individuals with a deep understanding of cloud development grows.</p>

<h2 id="5g-and-iot">5G and IoT</h2>

<p>With the next generation of the Internet of Things (IoT) and always-connected devices, 5G and lightning-fast internet will be critical. As consumers look to businesses to solve their problems, developers are seeing vast opportunities.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“It is in the intersection of 5G and IoT where the next generation of transformations will arrive from,” — <a href="https://www.techrepublic.com/article/developers-these-are-the-top-skills-you-will-need-in-2021/" target="_blank">Tom Canning</a>, VP of IoT at Canonical</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The demand for augmented reality, resource-intensive apps, and Connected Technologies knowhow will only grow with 5G. Developers will be needed to help not only keep smartphones running smoothly, but to keep the “smartification” of entire city grids online.</p>

<h2 id="devsecops-ftw">DevSecOps FTW</h2>

<p>As we mentioned many businesses are looking to keep their tech stacks reliable and shore up defenses during these times of adversity. The modernization of apps and services has also brought renewed attention to cybersecurity issues.</p>

<p>“…Job openings for cybersecurity engineers increased by 20 percent from February to March 2020, indicating an increased need for employers to defend their data and networks. Cybercriminals have taken advantage of the scattered work environment created by COVID-19 to perform phishing and various cyber-attacks.” — <a href="https://blog.crowdbotics.com/easiest-and-hardest-developer-skills-to-hire-for-in-2021/" target="_blank">Easiest and Hardest Developer Skills to Hire For in 2021</a></p>

<p>Digital transformation isn’t the only concern. The “new normal” and #WorkFromAnywhere revolution requires DevSecOps to think about how teams communicate remotely with new scrutiny.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“And with the world switching to remote working, developers with cloud architecture and cybersecurity skills for the cloud are going to be highly sought after.” — Co-founder and CCO of CodinGame, Aude Barral</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="hybridized-business-means-flexible-roles">Hybridized business means flexible roles</h2>

<p>These big shifts in how teams work together are forcing most businesses to rethink their strategies. Upskilling and reskilling have become hot topics as industries pivot to focusing on hiring from within.</p>

<p>Strategic thinking is in higher demand than ever to keep up with the ever-changing times. Individual roles are being rebranded by what niche skill sets developers can bring to the table.</p>

<p>And <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/02/6-soft-skills-every-developer-needs-to-get-hired/" target="_blank">soft skills</a> are more important for IT pros than ever, “… Around<a href="https://financesonline.com/recruitment-trends/" target="_blank"> 66% of all new jobs</a> will mainly rely on soft skills. Some of such top soft skills are collaboration, problem-solving, and communication.”</p>

<p>Full-stack developers who can think outside of the box, communicate effectively, and have a repertoire of both front and back-end programming languages will win the day.</p>

<h2 id="global-pools-of-talented-innovators">Global pools of talented innovators</h2>

<p>As a community that promotes ongoing <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/12/21/the-developer-s-guide-to-managing-your-business-part-one/" target="_blank">education, support, and success</a>, we only go as far as you do. There’s never been a better time to be a digital expert.</p>

<p>Connecting top IT pros across the globe is our thing. That’s why we created our network of like-minded innovators to help share inspiration, learn from one another, and gain work experience.</p>

<p>Esteemed teams work smarter. With the right help, you can take on projects, make a profit, and quit your day job (or make more on your side hustle).</p>

<p>We’re always here to lend a hand. If you haven’t already, <a href="https://join.slack.com/t/esteemed/shared_invite/zt-aejwraa8-mFs6ZUEs6voPD5RCV3vwvg">join us today</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kelton Reid</name></author><category term="Developer Life" /><category term="Contracting Tips" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As industries fast-track their digital transformation to stay afloat, the demand for top tech talent has never been higher.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/jefferson-santos-9socnyqmkzi-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/jefferson-santos-9socnyqmkzi-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Integrate Mindfulness in Hiring</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/02/08/how-to-integrate-mindfulness-in-hiring/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Integrate Mindfulness in Hiring" /><published>2021-02-08T22:31:30+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-08T22:31:30+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/02/08/how-to-integrate-mindfulness-in-hiring</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/02/08/how-to-integrate-mindfulness-in-hiring/"><![CDATA[<p>Sourcing talent and hiring new employees are some of the most challenging — and important — tasks that managers face. We all know the feeling of being overwhelmed by the process, despite our best laid plans and intentions. How often do we hire the candidate who looks to be the right person, only to find ourselves recruiting for the same position just a few short months later when the new hire doesn’t work out?</p>

<p>The truth is that we aren’t always good at hiring. We might talk ourselves into thinking we’ve found the right person simply to end a process that has taken up more time and resources than we’re willing to spare. We may, conversely, drag out the hiring process indefinitely in the search for the “perfect” person. We might have two great candidates and no way to decide between them. And, frankly, we may find the process a distraction if we have pressing work or family obligations.</p>

<p>Our issues with hiring are rarely a result of not having good candidates from which to choose. More often than not, our challenges are the result of our own lack of self-awareness. In decision-making, we often fall back on impulses and miss out on a great candidate because we don’t realize we can make better choices. Finding ways to be open and objective can be elusive, especially if we feel pressured to get the hiring done.</p>

<p>Rather than relying on our intuition, we can turn towards mindfulness to aid us in the hiring process. Jon Kabat-Zinn, the father of secular mindfulness, defines mindfulness as paying attention on purpose, in the present moment, and without judgment. Mindfulness is a way of being, often practiced through meditation, that teaches us to focus and concentrate, to be aware of our emotions and thoughts, and to cultivate acceptance.</p>

<p>Let’s examine how mindfulness can help us make better hiring decisions.</p>

<h3 id="active-listening"><strong>Active Listening</strong></h3>

<p>There can be no communication without listening, and while it’s safe to say that most of us have never taken a class in listening, it is the cornerstone of all our relationships and one of the greatest skills we can cultivate. When we fail to listen deeply, we risk misinterpreting the conversation. We may, for example, find ourselves only half listening to what is being said. Even worse, we might focus too much of our attention on how we are going to respond, and completely miss both the words and the underlying subtleties being expressed.</p>

<p>Mindful listening is about setting an intention to listen. According to <a href="https://www.mindful.org/how-to-practice-mindful-listening/">Mindful</a> magazine, we can follow the HEAR process:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Halt – give your full attention to the speaker</li>
  <li>Enjoy – take a breath to absorb what is being said, whether positive or negative</li>
  <li>Ask – conduct self-inquiry; do you really understand, or are you making assumptions?</li>
  <li>Reflect – repeat (in your own words) what you heard to validate your understanding</li>
</ol>

<p>Mute your phone, pause notifications, and give your undivided attention on your candidate. Consider asking a predefined set of open-ended questions that you can use consistently with each candidate so that you can evaluate their soft skills. For example, ask questions such as, “Tell me about a time you were on a project that failed. What would you have done differently?”. This type of question allows you to move your focus from the candidate’s personality to their capability. You’ll get greater insight into how a candidate sees themselves in times of both triumph and adversity, too. Try to understand the other person’s perspective, even if you don’t embrace it as your own. By becoming better listeners, we open the door to being intentionally present during the interview process, without being clouded by judgment or emotion.</p>

<h3 id="overcoming-bias"><strong>Overcoming Bias</strong></h3>

<p>It is human nature for us to want to socialize with people with whom we identify. After the 2004 presidential election, a poll found that 57 percent of undecided voters would rather drink a beer with Bush than with Kerry. We’ve been using that question, “Who would you rather drink a beer with?” ever since.</p>

<p>Implicit bias is an automatic process that influences our hiring decisions. It’s our gut feeling. We may not realize that there exists a bias within ourselves in the areas of race, ethnicity, age, gender, socio-economic status, school attended, and even how a person looks, sounds, or dresses. But within 90 seconds of meeting a candidate, an opinion is formed. Although our decisions might seem genuinely objective, we often don’t recognize that the best person for the job was eliminated solely on the grounds of our own implicit bias.</p>

<p><a href="https://medium.com/inclusion-insights/mindfulness-bias-literature-review-3e4a9993cb41">Studies</a> show that mindfulness can reduce our tendency towards implicit bias. It is only when we become more conscious of our own bias that we can begin to make decisions from a place of greater objectivity. We say that mindfulness has two wings: wisdom and compassion. Tapping into these qualities makes deep change possible.</p>

<p><em>Wisdom:</em> Mindfulness requires that we pause our response in order to access higher brain function and make more intentional choices. Self-awareness is at the heart of mindfulness practice. Take the time to sit with your thoughts, emotions, and body sensations for a few minutes each day. Notice your patterns without engaging with the narrative. With time, you will find that you will be able to respond more intentionally, rather than reacting in the moment. Bring that self-awareness into the hiring process, and you can begin to access your propensity for bias.</p>

<p><em>Compassion:</em> Have you ever realized your tendency to beat yourself up over a mistake you’ve made, whereas if it’s your best friend who’s made the error, you’re much more accepting? As we begin to notice our own bias, we may find that our values aren’t as aligned with our actions as we thought. This can lead us to feel uncomfortable and to criticize or blame ourselves for not being “better.” Self-compassion training, particularly loving-kindness meditation, allows us to see that deep down, we are all part of a greater humanity and deserve respect and kindness. The beautiful thing is that once we find self-compassion, we show more compassion to those around us — especially to those who are different from us.</p>

<p>Mindfulness teaches us to turn inwards and constantly question our motives and actions. We then can begin to notice our bias triggers and replace them with more objective evaluation metrics. By lessening our cognitive bias, we improve decision making and the bottom line.</p>

<h3 id="leading-with-intention"><strong>Leading with Intention</strong></h3>

<p>We <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/328274">lead with intention</a> when we focus on guiding and engaging employees to meet their full potential. This includes sharing a vision of where the company wants to move and how to make it properly positioned for the future. When we infuse the hiring process with intention, we are creating a culture of acceptance in which we honor what each employee brings to the table.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s time to leave behind the concept of “cultural fit” and replace it with “cultural contribution.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We can foster team building not by hiring people who are exactly like those currently on the team, but by bringing together people with valuable unique contributions. This drives innovation, creativity, and diversity, thereby allowing our organization to grow and adapt to its environment, new trends, and the needs of our audience.</p>

<p>To get out of your autopilot hiring mode, practice mindfulness. Everyone has their own unique ways in which they’ll contribute to your company culture. Mindfulness will help you cultivate the deep self-inquiry necessary for building an intentional team that embraces those differences. In doing so, you’ll not only set your employees up for true success, but lower the risk that they won’t work out in the role for which you hired them.</p>

<p>Mindfulness enhances clarity and focus. It allows us to recognize the value of multiple perspectives and backgrounds, and it builds compassion for ourselves and those around us. When we question our beliefs, sit with the uncomfortable, and cultivate acceptance, we take a step towards creating a workplace that attracts dedicated employees who are eager to take on our vision.</p>]]></content><author><name>Dori Kelner</name></author><category term="Hiring Strategy" /><category term="Talent Sourcing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sourcing talent and hiring new employees are some of the most challenging — and important — tasks that managers face. Let’s examine how mindfulness can help us make better hiring decisions.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-jopwell-2422291.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-jopwell-2422291.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">8 Ways 2020 Impacted Workplaces and Hiring</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/01/26/8-ways-2020-impacted-workplaces-and-hiring/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="8 Ways 2020 Impacted Workplaces and Hiring" /><published>2021-01-26T15:49:12+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-26T15:49:12+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/01/26/8-ways-2020-impacted-workplaces-and-hiring</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/01/26/8-ways-2020-impacted-workplaces-and-hiring/"><![CDATA[<p>It’s a huge understatement to say that 2020 made an impact on economies around the world, let alone workplaces and hiring practices. As the concentric circles of crises converged, our personal, local, and global outlooks shifted like never before.</p>

<p>As we all settle in to the “new normal,” the challenge of landing talented tech pros remains high. Our need to adopt future proof <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/11/02/small-business-big-problems-tips-for-sourcing-talent-as-a-small-business/" target="_blank">talent sourcing</a>, hiring, and retention is greater than ever.</p>

<p>Streamlining the process is still top-of-mind for most CTOs, especially during this perilous time in history. One-size-fits-all recruitment, generic job listings, and backward-looking retention strategies are a thing of the past.</p>

<p>With the harnessing of big data, the cloud, and the surge in video conferencing — yes Zoom, Slack, and Meet are officially verbs — we’ve all entered the #futureofwork.</p>

<p>Let’s take a spin through eight important developments in this updated world of work and talent acquisition.</p>

<h3 id="the-arrival-of-a-global-talent-pool">The arrival of a global talent pool</h3>

<p>At the height of the pandemic 50-70% of the US workforce was working remotely. Two-thirds or more say they want to continue doing so for the foreseeable future.</p>

<p>Agile, distributed teams have been a necessary sea change for many big tech companies like Google, Twitter, Microsoft, and Facebook. And their employees say that without a remote option in the future, they’ll be unlikely to stay.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Remote work tantalizes with its promises of diverse talent pools, increased productivity and retention, and savings on salaries and facilities, not to mention smaller carbon footprint.” — <a href="https://www.owllabs.com/state-of-remote-work/2020" target="_blank">State of Remote Work 2020</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Work From Anywhere is now a benefit to both candidates and employers. And in our hyper-connected world, we have access to a global talent pool of top tech candidates.</p>

<ul>
  <li>In 2020, the use of company video meetings grew 50% more than pre-pandemic</li>
  <li>77% of employees agree that post-pandemic, a work from home (WFH) option would make them happier</li>
  <li>75% have been the same or more productive during COVID-19 while WFH</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="exploding-the-traditional-talent-acquisition-model">Exploding the traditional Talent Acquisition model</h3>

<p>Contactless recruitment and virtual hiring are booming. High tech HR and hybrid workforces have become commonplace for businesses and brands to ensure safety and efficiency.</p>

<p>But companies are also thinking about more than streamlining time-to-hire, they’re thinking about nurturing long-term relationships and building diverse, global, A-list teams.</p>

<p>The employee value proposition (EVP) has become top-of-mind for many recruiters as a holistic approach to building innovative teams. This process starts long before the job listing for most.</p>

<p>By building a culture that resonates with prospective employees you can <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/11/02/small-business-big-problems-tips-for-sourcing-talent-as-a-small-business/" target="_blank">boost talent sourcing and retention</a>. And it’s one of the top reasons talent will choose to work with you.</p>

<p>93% of employees <a href="https://www.glassdoor.com/employers/resources/hr-and-recruiting-stats/" target="_blank">mention the importance of company culture</a> in their online job reviews. They want to not only feel like your brand is worthy to put on a resume, but also that your mission and values align with their own.</p>

<h3 id="artificial-intelligence-vs-hiring-for-soft-skills">Artificial intelligence vs hiring for soft skills</h3>

<p>HR automation tools and the desire to up your business’ digital IQ are trending. But as we’ve discussed <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/01/14/is-your-approach-to-hiring-wrong/" target="_blank">the perils of the hiring industrial complex</a>, most of the solutions you’re being sold don’t have results to back them up.</p>

<p>A focus on soft skills and retention is the new, main focus for many businesses thinking beyond simple hiring algorithms. Looking beyond the resume is a tactic smart businesses are employing worldwide.</p>

<p>“… Around 66% of all new jobs will mainly rely on soft skills. Some of such top soft skills are collaboration, problem-solving, and communication.” — <a href="https://financesonline.com/recruitment-trends/" target="_blank">10 Recruitment Trends for 2020/2021</a></p>

<p><strong>Top 10 Soft Skills in the Future of Work:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Sense-making</li>
  <li>Novel and Adaptive Thinking</li>
  <li>Social Intelligence</li>
  <li>Trans-disciplinarity</li>
  <li>New Media Literacy</li>
  <li>Computational Thinking</li>
  <li>Cognitive Load Management</li>
  <li>Design Mindset</li>
  <li>Cross-Cultural Competency</li>
  <li>Virtual Collaboration</li>
</ul>

<p>Source: Institute for the Future &amp; Univ. of Phoenix Research Institute</p>

<h2 id="fast-forward-to-upskillingreskilling-current-employees">Fast-forward to upskilling/reskilling current employees</h2>

<p>Cross-functional has taken on a whole new meaning in 2021. As many companies seek to do more with less, they’re looking to internally upskill or reskill their current employees.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Reskilling is defined as training for employees who have shown they have the aptitude for learning a completely new occupation…. Upskilling focuses on providing training for employees who need to learn new skills to improve their current performance without changing their position or career path.” — <a href="https://blogs.managementconcepts.com/2020/01/31/tell-me-what-is-the-difference-between-reskilling-and-upskilling/" target="_blank">U.S. Office of Personnel Management</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>With internal mobility on the rise, look for a recommitment to investing in the most talented team members. Verified and transferable skill sets, adaptability, and resilience are in high demand.</p>

<h3 id="flexibility-and-efficiency-at-the-forefront">Flexibility and efficiency at the forefront</h3>

<p>Without a daily commute, the definitions of a workday and work-life balance have shifted dramatically. But that doesn’t mean we’re getting less done; quite the opposite.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“On average, remote employees worked an extra 26 hours each month during COVID (nearly an extra day every week).” — State of Remote Work 2020</p>
</blockquote>

<p>With the latest data about the counterintuitive output of diverse, globally distributed teams, the 9-to-5 model is getting tossed in the trash.</p>

<p>Innovation starts with processes that embrace the flexible schedules and multiple timezones of top talent. And success stories are legion when these models are employed by future-thinking HR teams.</p>

<h3 id="empathy-diversity-and-equity">Empathy, diversity, and equity</h3>

<p>Actions will speak louder than words in the coming years. With social justice, the pandemic, climate change, and so much uncertainty around the world, your brand is more vulnerable than ever.</p>

<p>Transparency and equity have become tantamount to success. Showing that you understand the day-to-day struggles of your team members — and their communities — will help win the hearts and minds of future candidates.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Diversity, equity, and inclusion in the workplace will become a real driver of employment decisions. Increasingly, the best talent will look for visible evidence of a company’s commitment to diversity within the interview process, within the hiring team, and within the executive leadership of the company.” — <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/carinvanvuuren/" target="_blank">Carin Van Vuuren, CMO at Greenhouse Software</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Skills, not country of origin or cultural orientation, define the talent of the future. By broadcasting inclusion and accountability, businesses can embrace and incorporate the next generation of stars.</p>

<h3 id="mental-health-awareness-and-acknowledgment">Mental health awareness and acknowledgment</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>“It goes without saying that this pandemic coupled with the social and political unrest of this year has exacerbated the stress, anxiety, depression, and mental health issues of workers.” — <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/heidilynnekurter/2021/12/30/5-ways-2020-has-impacted-workplaces-and-how-it-will-change-in-2021/" target="_blank">5 Ways 2020 Has Impacted Workplaces And How It Will Change In 2021</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Mimicking in-office culture in the Matrix of Zoom meetings has become exhausting. As we try to maintain some touchstone of normality, burnout has crept in with the overuse of technology.</p>

<p>“No meeting days” are trending for overall sanity and output. 80% of employees now believe that there should be one day a week with no meetings.</p>

<p>Meditation, yoga, and therapy are being encouraged by C-level executives as a replacement. Flexibility is taking on a whole new meaning in the boardroom and beyond.</p>

<h3 id="deep-pools-of-talent-are-the-future"><strong>Deep pools of talent are the future</strong></h3>

<p>At Esteemed we’ve made it our goal to remove the guesswork of staffing digital. We’ve spent the last decade sourcing one of the most talented and diverse communities in tech.</p>

<p>Employers can browse hundreds of talented digital professionals we’ve personally vetted. And we’ve integrated every step of the process into one simple Slack channel.</p>

<p>Esteemed teams work smarter. Make a request and be collaborate with trusted pros almost instantly.</p>

<p>We are some of the brightest digital minds in the business, and we are colleagues recommending colleagues. It’s a win-win.</p>

<p>Let us take some of the burden off of your talent sourcing strategies. <a href="/get-a-quote/">Drop us a line</a> today to share your staffing needs!</p>]]></content><author><name>Kelton Reid</name></author><category term="Distributed Workforce" /><category term="Hiring Strategy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the “new normal” the challenge of landing top tech pros remains high. Future proof talent sourcing, hiring, and retention for the win.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/christina-wocintechchat-com-ldap559l-mu-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/christina-wocintechchat-com-ldap559l-mu-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Your Approach to Hiring Wrong?</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/01/14/is-your-approach-to-hiring-wrong/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Your Approach to Hiring Wrong?" /><published>2021-01-14T15:17:50+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-14T15:17:50+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/01/14/is-your-approach-to-hiring-wrong</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2021/01/14/is-your-approach-to-hiring-wrong/"><![CDATA[<p>We know the unique challenge today’s businesses face hiring top tech talent. There’s never been more demand or <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/30/why-demand-for-tech-talent-is-so-high/">fewer qualified IT pros</a> actively searching for positions.</p>

<p>And most agencies and brands plan to up their digital IQs in the coming wave of Industry 4.0. That’s why landing the best developers for your ongoing project needs is still the #1 concern in the executive suite.</p>

<p>“PwC’s 2017 CEO survey reports that chief executives view the unavailability of talent and skills as the biggest threat to their business.” — <a href="https://hbr.org/2019/05/your-approach-to-hiring-is-all-wrong">Your Approach to Hiring Is All Wrong, HBR</a></p>

<p>That hasn’t changed, in fact it’s only gotten more dire. And it’s no secret that the hiring industrial complex has become a drain on resources with little proven benefit.</p>

<h3 id="why-the-futureofwork-is-about-more-than-just-filling-your-funnel-with-warm-bodies">Why the #FutureofWork is about more than just filling your funnel with warm bodies</h3>

<p>40% of US companies now outsource their hiring process. These recruitment outsourcers then use subcontractors to scour LinkedIn and social media sites for passive candidates.</p>

<p>It’s why currently employed IT pros report being contacted multiple times a day about their interest to change jobs. Keeping your top tech employees has become a war of the “highest bidder.”</p>

<p>But it doesn’t have to be a game killer. We’ve talked about how <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/11/02/small-business-big-problems-tips-for-sourcing-talent-as-a-small-business/">smaller businesses can compete to stand out in the minds of prospects</a>.</p>

<p>And making your weaknesses your strengths is not about going toe-to-toe on salary, compensation, or benefits packages. It’s about sourcing talent with an eye to the future.</p>

<h3 id="is-your-hiring-approach-backward-looking-or-future-proof">Is your hiring approach backward-looking or future proof?</h3>

<p>Making the best possible choice on who to hire for your team has become increasingly difficult. But the hardest part isn’t necessarily which overseas vendor or software to outsource it to.</p>

<p>With over a decade of expertise helping brands and agencies source respected developers, we see this mistake a lot. It’s a lack of foresight toward <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/09/how-digital-talent-sourcing-can-help-you-avoid-bad-hires/">sourcing for culture and retention</a>.</p>

<p>The toughest part about building an A-class team is still how to architect success. And how to do it in the most efficient and complementary way for your business.</p>

<p>Having access to a deep pool of proven, respected, and vetted talent has become a huge commodity. And we know this from experience.</p>

<h3 id="big-data-and-hiring-algorithms-wont-save-your-business">Big data and hiring algorithms won’t save your business</h3>

<p>In the long run, those passive IT hot shots aren’t necessarily worth the investment, sadly. And companies already throw $20 billion a year at human resource vendors when they don’t have to.</p>

<p>Outsourced candidates don’t always contribute right away, and this can be disruptive to current employees. There’s also no evidence that passive hires are of a higher quality, and they often take longer to onboard to potential.</p>

<p>This unsustainable model of outsourcing, filling the funnel, and hiring unknown commodities can actually drain resources over time. And no one can afford that right now.</p>

<p>Outsourcing your hiring to recruitment farms won’t solve your two bigger problems: Time-to-hire and quality-of-hire. And more algorithms fail to factor in vectors specific to your exact business.</p>

<h3 id="is-your-applicant-tracking-software-worth-the-headache">Is your applicant-tracking software worth the headache?</h3>

<p>That applicant-tracking software you think will save you money, may actually <a href="https://hbr.org/2019/05/data-science-cant-fix-hiring-yet">cost you in company culture</a>. It might seem nifty out of the box, but are their proven benefits to measuring body language?</p>

<p>Algorithms and so-called efficiency bots lack the context of what’s needed most in the sourcing through retention processes. The human touch, and the structure and proven vetting that actually get results.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, analytics are often flawed and backward-looking. We’ve never experienced such an important and innovative time in our culture than right now.</p>

<p>With the rise of cutting-edge tech — and the necessary players to implement it —there’s no question that your hiring process needs to be seamless.</p>

<p>“Artificial intelligence (AI), blockchain, Internet of Things (IoT), virtual reality, 3D printing, and combinations of these, are viewed as cost-cutting and revenue-generating opportunities.” — <a href="https://www.pwc.com/us/en/library/ceo-agenda/ceo-survey.html">PwC’s 2020 CEO Survey</a></p>

<h3 id="dont-go-pound-for-pound-with-hiring-gorillas-without-help">Don’t go pound-for-pound with hiring gorillas without help</h3>

<p>When it comes to auditing your hiring and acquisition strategies we know there are always questions on how to save time and money. But there’s no obvious shortcut to success.</p>

<p>Why not trust a talent sourcing network with a proven track record? Lean on structured and standardized processes to find a more inclusive, diverse, and effective team.</p>

<p>We are Esteemed, colleagues recommending colleagues. Top digital problem-solvers at the touch of a button.</p>

<h3 id="recruitment-and-retention-start-by-sourcing-talent-smarter">Recruitment and retention start by sourcing talent smarter</h3>

<p>Save yourself the headache and enlist help from the start. The key to the Fourth Industrial Revolution is access to deeper networks of talented and diverse voices.</p>

<p>We rub elbows with talented developers every day who can speak to your needs.</p>

<p>We’d love to chat about all of your hiring needs! Drop us a line anytime.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kelton Reid</name></author><category term="Hiring Strategy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We know the challenge today’s businesses face hiring top tech talent. But is your approach to hiring draining needed resources?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-photo-4099096.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/pexels-photo-4099096.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Developer’s Guide to Managing Your Business: Part Two</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/12/29/the-developer-s-guide-to-managing-your-business-part-two/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Developer’s Guide to Managing Your Business: Part Two" /><published>2020-12-29T20:41:14+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-29T20:41:14+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/12/29/the-developer-s-guide-to-managing-your-business-part-two</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/12/29/the-developer-s-guide-to-managing-your-business-part-two/"><![CDATA[<p>Now that you’ve zeroed in on your target audience and researched the ins-and-outs of your niche market you can outfit your business with the essentials.</p>

<p><a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/12/21/the-developer-s-guide-to-managing-your-business-part-one/">In Part One you established</a> your minimum viable business (MVB), or product (MVP) to move ahead with a modest investment of time and resources.</p>

<p>The leaner the better at the outset, so take the Occam’s Razor business approach. The simplest answer is often the correct one, for now.</p>

<p>For developers planning to sell their IT expertise as a service, you’ll still need to network with like-minded peers. Contribute regularly to community networks and stay involved in coding events and camps.</p>

<p>Remember, “Know, like, and trust” is how you <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/30/why-demand-for-tech-talent-is-so-high/">establish your reputation as an authority</a> in your niche. This makes it far easier to leverage your relationships into a viable service or product people need. As a freelancer, you’ve already …</p>

<ul>
  <li>Determined your rate range, low to high;</li>
  <li>Defined the type of work you like most and are best at;</li>
  <li>Committed to seeking out contracts based on timing;</li>
  <li>And planned to layer at least two contracts concurrently for “insurance” purposes.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="rise-and-grind-is-a-harmful-myth">‘Rise and Grind’ is a harmful myth</h3>

<p>We mentioned that <em>burnout</em> is a real thing in our industry, and your mental health is a precious commodity, so pace yourself. Create a sane and sustainable business model.</p>

<p>With over a decade of expertise helping place talented developers with businesses and brands, we’re your biggest fans. Never be afraid to ask for help, especially from trusted communities of like-minded coders.</p>

<p>You’ll know you’re ready to go when:</p>

<ul>
  <li>You’ve narrowed your MVB or MVP based on feedback and research</li>
  <li>Found your service or product-market fit through iteration</li>
  <li>You’re ready to set up all the things!</li>
</ul>

<p>With a solid path forward you can dig into the working parts of your business. “Just get started” is our mantra, and there’s no other way.</p>

<h3 id="time-is-money-and-yours-is-invaluable">‘Time is money’ and yours is invaluable</h3>

<p>As you prepare to venture out as a contractor or software savior never forget that your greatest asset is you. Don’t let prospects take advantage of your expertise.</p>

<p>Doctors and lawyers charge astronomical hourly fees for a reason. They’ve established themselves as well-trusted professionals in their field.</p>

<p>Now that you’ve established yourself as the go-to authority in your niche you’re ready to make good on your promise.</p>

<p>Whether your business plan entails <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/241035">SaaS</a>, coaching, consulting, courses, or straight-ahead freelancing you’ll need the business basics kit:</p>

<p>1. Create a unique LLC for your brand</p>

<ul>
  <li>Your Secretary of State</li>
  <li>LegalZoom</li>
</ul>

<p>2. Get accounting software to invoice clients and keep track of time and expenses</p>

<ul>
  <li>Freshbooks</li>
  <li>Quickbooks</li>
</ul>

<p>3. Find business insurance to protect yourself from liabilities</p>

<ul>
  <li>Hiscox</li>
  <li>Local Agent</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Note: If you’re working on a SaaS product, there <a href="https://www.infoq.com/articles/advice-software-startup/">will be far more legalese</a> and IP rigamarole. You’ll also need to plan on a longer timeline/runway to launch.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>(Disclosure: We’re not lawyers)</p>

<p>4. And create a <a href="https://foundr.com/marketing-strategy">marketing plan</a> that includes Owned, Earned, and Paid media channels</p>

<ul>
  <li>Website and email list</li>
  <li>Github or community contributions and involvement</li>
  <li>Google Adwords, Facebook ads, sponsored updates on Twitter, or Instagram</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="abcs-of-how-to-keep-work-coming-in">ABCs of how to keep work coming in</h3>

<p>We hear this question all the time, “Sure I want to freelance, but how do I keep the work coming?” Here are a few solutions for establishing a foundation for the long haul:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Your LinkedIn profile</strong>: Your personal web page connected to a search engine specifically for your skills and experience. Don’t make the mistake of wasting it.</li>
  <li><strong>Job boards</strong>: As a tight-knit community, we can keep an eye on just a few places to capture <a href="https://talent.esteemed.io/jobs">new opportunities</a>.</li>
  <li><strong>Client career pages</strong>: Your best clients are your existing clients. Keep an eye on past client career pages. As needs arise, reach out and offer your assistance.</li>
</ul>

<p>Important factors to keep in mind doing client work:</p>

<ul>
  <li>80% of your volume is going to come from 20% of your clients, focus on expanding those relationships;</li>
  <li>Communication is the key to building and maintaining relationships;</li>
  <li>Your best clients are often your existing ones;</li>
  <li>Define your criteria for a “good client”;</li>
  <li>Quickly dispense with those that don’t to save time and money.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="no-one-needs-a-drill-bit-they-need-a-hole-in-the-wall">No one needs a drill bit, they need a hole in the wall</h3>

<p>“Benefits not features” is a great marketing slogan you can adopt. No one needs more software, what they need is the timeliest solution to their problem.</p>

<p>When devising your business plan be sure to develop an <a href="https://blog.hubspot.com/marketing/buyer-persona-research">ongoing client or buyer persona</a>. This will help you to stay in tune with their “hopes, fears, and dreams.”</p>

<p>Your niche audience or market will change over the years, just like all markets. And remember that markets are conversations. Be sure to speak to your clients in their language to establish effective communications throughout your relationship.</p>

<p>Staying relevant (and in-demand) means adjusting your product-market fit iteratively. We like to lean on the Japanese concept of “Kaizen” which refers to taking small steps each day to reach your goal.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Master one to three specific tasks, especially ones you’re good at;</li>
  <li>Niche skills are great, but complementary niche skills are better;</li>
  <li>Focus on improving in areas you are weaker;</li>
  <li>Obtain certifications in niche disciplines and languages;</li>
  <li>Obtain endorsements on LinkedIn;</li>
  <li>Take code screenings on LinkedIn and CoderByte (used by Esteemed).</li>
</ul>

<p>This is by no means an exhaustive list of ideas to help you along your journey. After a decade of helping IT pros connect with clients, we understand that learning is a life-long process.</p>

<h3 id="easy-money-is-damn-hard-work">Easy money is damn hard work</h3>

<p>Now that you’ve got your business and marketing plans honed you’re primed to reach your target customers. By continuing to build your brand awareness and study the competition you’ll set yourself up for ongoing success.</p>

<p>As you build out your sales funnel, each quarter will continue to get easier and pay dividends. But that doesn’t mean you’ll be able to rest on your laurels.</p>

<p>There are multiple opportunities for establishing monthly recurring revenue (MRR) for yourself including:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Monthly maintenance - use or lose hour blocks, be competitive, make some offshore friends to support;</li>
  <li>Audits - monthly security, SEO, or ongoing strategy audits can add to MRR options;</li>
  <li>Content strategy and production - if you are a developer, hire someone to do the work, add a margin on top;</li>
  <li>Retainers - ongoing consulting and feature enhancements.</li>
</ul>

<p>By continuing to keep up with industry trends and network with your peers you’ll not only improve your entrepreneurial skills but also your standing in the community.</p>

<p>That’s where we come in…</p>

<h3 id="were-always-here-to-lend-a-hand">We’re always here to lend a hand</h3>

<p>As a community that promotes ongoing education, support, and prosperity, we only go as far as you do. That’s why we’ve created a network of like-minded problem-solvers with a commitment to excellence.</p>

<p>With the right help, you can take on projects, make a profit, ditch your day job, or launch a highly-profitable side hustle!</p>

<p>If you missed the first in our series start here: <strong>The Developer’s Guide to Managing Your Business: Part One</strong>.</p>

<p>See you out there.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kelton Reid</name></author><category term="Contracting Tips" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[With over a decade of expertise helping companies connect with talented IT professionals, we’ve seen the benefits of starting a business firsthand.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/andy-holmes-webyw4nsfpg-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/andy-holmes-webyw4nsfpg-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Developer’s Guide to Managing Your Business: Part One</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/12/21/the-developer-s-guide-to-managing-your-business-part-one/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Developer’s Guide to Managing Your Business: Part One" /><published>2020-12-21T21:10:02+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-21T21:10:02+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/12/21/the-developer-s-guide-to-managing-your-business-part-one</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/12/21/the-developer-s-guide-to-managing-your-business-part-one/"><![CDATA[<p>Are you thinking about venturing out on your own to start a software development or contracting business? Then it occurs to you, “How the heck do I go from idea to service or product?”</p>

<p>It’s a challenging journey, and not for the faint of heart. It’s also not nearly as hard as you think. Instantly you’ll start dreaming about that big exit. But seriously, stop that now!</p>

<p>You don’t have to be the next Bill Gates or Sergey Brin. But it’s not as easy as just hanging up a digital shingle and going to the ATM.</p>

<p>The truth is, with a small investment and the right motivation, you can easily be making <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/30/why-demand-for-tech-talent-is-so-high/" target="_blank">twice your day job salary</a>. And you’ll make your own hours if you’re savvy!</p>

<h3 id="the-journey-of-1000-miles-starts-with-one-step">The journey of 1000 miles starts with one step</h3>

<p>Whether you want to do freelance work as a ronin IT pro, or finally commit to your software solution, just start! The best advice any entrepreneur ever received was to simply get going.</p>

<p>Everyone has an idea for a book, movie, or app that they want to create or write. But the reality is, not everyone has the growth mindset (or energy) to start down that path.</p>

<p>No one ever said being your own boss would be easy, and it won’t be. It’s a marathon, not a sprint.</p>

<p>Here’s a brief guide to help you get started on your journey.</p>

<h3 id="why-start-freelancing">Why start freelancing?</h3>

<p>With over a decade of expertise helping businesses and brands <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/07/25/5-reasons-why-you-should-join-a-talent-network/" target="_blank">connect with talented contract developers</a> we’ve seen the benefits firsthand:</p>

<ul>
  <li>You can make more money and have work-life balance</li>
  <li>Work on a variety of projects to build your resume and street cred</li>
  <li>Control your own schedule</li>
  <li>Quit your day job</li>
  <li>Build a brand, or small agency</li>
  <li>And create an exit strategy as a “producer”</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="know-your-intended-niche-and-market">Know your intended niche and market</h3>

<p>Out of the gate, you’ll need to find out if anyone really wants your offerings. And by digging down into <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/encyclopedia/unique-selling-proposition-usp" target="_blank">your unique selling prop as a developer</a> you’ll be able to differentiate your skillset.</p>

<p>“Did you know that GitLab was built for the specific needs of one of the cofounders and he had no intention of turning it into a business?” — <a href="https://medium.com/practical-programming-weekly/how-to-start-a-business-as-a-software-developer-9370af88fe24" target="_blank">How to start a business as a Software developer</a></p>

<p>If it’s your services you intend to hawk then you’ll want to make sure they’re in demand. And if it’s a product solution for the open market, you’re going to have to research your competition.</p>

<p>And I don’t mean do a few Google searches. You’ll need to get in the trenches and get boots on the ground intel.</p>

<p>Research your intended target market well ahead of any wireframing or launch. You’ll need to dig deep into the specifics of why exactly your service or solution is something people will pay for.</p>

<p>Developers are natural problem-solvers, so this is ground zero for any serious business venture.</p>

<h3 id="learn-how-to-sell-yourself">Learn how to sell yourself</h3>

<p>Some of the best advice we can give freelancers is learning how to market yourself. You’ll need to learn a few basics to get your services in front of clients.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Outbound activity on LinkedIn, phone calls to those that might consume your services</li>
  <li>Define deeper niches (non-profits, agencies, government)</li>
  <li>Target your most excited, qualified, profitable leads and customers</li>
</ul>

<p>Understanding the Pareto Principle – that 80% of your revenue will come from 20% of your customers – is a natural law and a proven business tactic. We swear by it.</p>

<h3 id="target-audiences-will-help-you-zero-in">Target audiences will help you zero in</h3>

<p>Once you’ve done your research and learned the ins-and-outs of your niche market you can get building. If you’re venturing out as a freelancer you’ll need a few basics before you go where the jobs are.</p>

<p>Establishing your minimum viable business (MVB), or product (MVP) will let you move ahead with less friction and investment of time and money. The leaner the better at the outset.</p>

<p>For developers who plan to sell their coding expertise as a service, you’ll need to network with like-minded professionals. Join networks and go to coding events and camps to rub elbows.</p>

<p>“Know, like, and trust” is how you’ll build your reputation as an authority in your niche. From there you’ll be able to leverage your relationships into a viable service or product people really need.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Demand outpaces supply, don’t undersell yourself;</li>
  <li>Listen to what the market is doing via recruiters;</li>
  <li>Set a rate range, low to high;</li>
  <li>Define the type of work you most enjoy, and are best at;</li>
  <li>Pick and choose contracts based on timing;</li>
  <li>It’s best to layer at least 2 contracts for “insurance” purposes.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="keep-the-passion-alive">Keep the passion alive!</h2>

<p>You have to make sure that this is something you’re passionate about for the long haul. Burnout is a real thing in our industry, and you’ll be putting in some serious hours to launch.</p>

<p><a href="" target="_blank">But never be afraid to ask for help</a>. Especially from a trusted community of like-minded professionals.</p>

<p>As you begin to formulate the thesis for your business, don’t forget the basics:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Research, research, research</li>
  <li>Narrow your MVB or MVP based on feedback</li>
  <li>Find your service or product-market fit through iteration</li>
  <li>Wash, rinse, repeat</li>
</ul>

<p>Forward progress always means learning from your mistakes and becoming slowly better over time. With a minimal investment and a head of steam you can be making money from clients in no time.</p>

<p>Just having your LLC designation and working for a few clients can be a dream business or a solid side-gig. But we’ll dig into more specifics that you’ll need to really get rolling in Part Two.</p>

<h3 id="never-doubt-that-a-small-group-of-committed-coders">Never doubt that a small group of committed coders…</h3>

<p>Can change the world. As a community that promotes ongoing education, support, and prosperity, we only go as far as you do.</p>

<p>That’s why we’ve created a community of like-minded problem-solvers with a commitment to excellence. We’re always here to lend a hand.</p>

<p>With the right help, you can take on projects, make a profit, and not have to stay at your day job, or make more money than you think!</p>

<p>Stay tuned for more specific resources and tools in <strong>The Developer’s Guide to Managing Your Business: Part Two</strong>. We’ll talk about specifics of launching your business and how to keep the work coming in.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kelton Reid</name></author><category term="Contracting Tips" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[With over a decade of expertise helping companies connect with talented contract developers we’ve seen the benefits of starting a business firsthand.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/paige-cody-ittqjs3upoy-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/paige-cody-ittqjs3upoy-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Work Specialized Recruiting into Your Hiring Strategy</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/12/07/how-to-work-specialized-recruiting-into-your-hiring-strategy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Work Specialized Recruiting into Your Hiring Strategy" /><published>2020-12-07T17:15:06+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-07T17:15:06+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/12/07/how-to-work-specialized-recruiting-into-your-hiring-strategy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/12/07/how-to-work-specialized-recruiting-into-your-hiring-strategy/"><![CDATA[<p>When it comes to auditing <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/11/02/small-business-big-problems-tips-for-sourcing-talent-as-a-small-business/" target="_blank">your talent sourcing</a> and acquisition strategies we know there are always questions on how to save time and money. But there’s no obvious shortcut to success.</p>

<p>If you’re lucky enough to have an in-house HR team you know how much each member juggles on a monthly basis. But if you’re a small startup or agency it might just come down to who wears the “hiring hat” that week.</p>

<p>When you’re looking for support who can you turn to? Many recruiting firms claim to have access to deep pools of specialized talent.</p>

<p>The reality is they’re looking at the same generic pool of candidates you are. And when it comes to landing top IT pros, the pickings are slim.</p>

<h3 id="specialized-vs-general-recruitment">Specialized vs. general recruitment</h3>

<p>We see the growing shortage of talented tech hires every day. It’s no mirage, and there are predicted to be <a href="https://jobbatical.com/resources/hiring-statistics" target="_blank">an additional 5 million IT jobs added</a> to that growing sea by 2027.</p>

<p>You wouldn’t go to a general practitioner to treat a highly specialized problem, would you? You would go to a specialist with expertise in that issue.</p>

<p>So by tapping into specialized recruiting to help you fill highly-technical roles you’re relying on specialists referring specialists. And this can give you a huge advantage.</p>

<h3 id="the-global-talent-shortage-is-real">The global talent shortage is real</h3>

<p>You’re not alone. <a href="https://go.manpowergroup.com/talent-shortage-2018#thereport" target="_blank">72% of employers report</a> having a hard time finding skilled candidates, especially for hard-to-fill positions. It’s also a growing epidemic that can impact your bottom line.</p>

<p>By enlisting the expertise of a niche specialist for your recruiting needs you can save invaluable resources. You’ll not only tap into a deeper pool of talent, but you can also boost time-to-hire and quality of hire.</p>

<p>Specialized recruiters become a natural extension of your HR team. Trusted envoys who can help broadcast your company culture and mission.</p>

<h3 id="time-to-hire-power-up">Time-to-hire power up</h3>

<p>Boosting time-to-hire not only saves you money, in the long run, it also boosts innovation. By taking the pressure off your recruiting team you’re freeing up time and brainpower.</p>

<p>Having someone vet your candidates for you takes the guesswork out of having to do multiple assessments and behavioral interviews yourself. This lets you focus on what really matters.</p>

<p><a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/02/6-soft-skills-every-developer-needs-to-get-hired/" target="_blank">Soft skills</a> are often overlooked by general recruiting firms because they’re more interested in warm bodies. Generalized recruiters don’t typically look beyond the resume.</p>

<p>But recruiters who can talk specifically to your most valued acquisitions’ needs do. And getting talented new hires in the door faster lets your team focus on their core competencies.</p>

<h3 id="culture-building-and-quality-of-hire">Culture-building and quality of hire</h3>

<p>A recent study by legacy employment site <a href="https://resources.careerbuilder.com/guides" target="_blank">CareerBuilder</a> found that 66% of US employers reported having been affected by a bad hire, with 27% saying a single bad hire cost them more than $50,000.</p>

<p>With a specialized recruiter, you’ll be building a team of contributing superstars right out of the gate. And specialists who speak the exact language of your business needs can help support your core values and diversity.</p>

<p>Lean on the tried-and-true experience of a specialty firm that talks the talk. Don’t play Russian roulette with your most trusted asset, your people.</p>

<h3 id="onboarding-and-the-race-for-talent">Onboarding and the race for talent</h3>

<p>We understand the pressure businesses face competing for top talent. Don’t try to go “pound-for-pound” with the big guys when you don’t have to.</p>

<p>Remember that recruitment and retention actually <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/09/how-digital-talent-sourcing-can-help-you-avoid-bad-hires/" target="_blank">start by sourcing talent smarter</a>. Not by trying to compete on salary, compensation, or benefits packages.</p>

<p>Save yourself the headache and enlist help from the start. The key to the next digital revolution will be access to deeper networks of talented and diverse voices.</p>

<p>We talk to developers every day who can speak to your needs. We are specialized colleagues recommending the best of the best.</p>

<p>We’d love to chat about all of your hiring needs! <a href="">Drop us a line anytime</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kelton Reid</name></author><category term="Hiring Strategy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Enlisting specialized recruiters to help fill highly-technical roles gives you a huge advantage. Specialists are a natural extension of your HR team.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/photo-1598257006460-4cd5d043cf49.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/photo-1598257006460-4cd5d043cf49.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Small Business, Big Problems: Tips for Sourcing Talent as a Small Business</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/11/02/small-business-big-problems-tips-for-sourcing-talent-as-a-small-business/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Small Business, Big Problems: Tips for Sourcing Talent as a Small Business" /><published>2020-11-02T22:46:40+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-02T22:46:40+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/11/02/small-business-big-problems-tips-for-sourcing-talent-as-a-small-business</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/11/02/small-business-big-problems-tips-for-sourcing-talent-as-a-small-business/"><![CDATA[<p>How can your small business compete for top talent? Maybe you’re a lean startup operating on a shoestring. That doesn’t mean you can’t attract impactful players to your team.</p>

<p>If the fight for talent was a boxing match, smaller businesses and larger companies aren’t in the same weight class. There’s no competition.</p>

<p>So getting innovative about how you stand out in the minds of prospects is the key. As the digital frontier becomes more competitive by the minute, any advantage helps.</p>

<h3 id="smaller-teams-are-scrappier">Smaller teams are scrappier</h3>

<p>Your weaknesses as a small business owner don’t have to be a disadvantage. The future of your business depends on <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/09/how-digital-talent-sourcing-can-help-you-avoid-bad-hires/" target="_blank">attracting the best candidates</a>.</p>

<p>But recruitment and retention actually start by sourcing talent differently. Not by going toe-to-toe on salary, compensation, or benefits packages.</p>

<p>Career fairs can give an unfair advantage to the big guys. You’ll need to go where talent is having conversations with each other, not where big brands are sucking the air from the room.</p>

<h3 id="70-of-the-global-workforce-is-passive-talent">70% of the global workforce is passive talent</h3>

<p>Top talent is <a href="https://financesonline.com/hiring-statistics/" title="Passive talent" target="_blank">passively job-hunting</a> all over the world and web. Though not actively looking for a gig, they’re always keeping an eye out for better things.</p>

<p>Speaking to them is not hard, and listening to their hopes and fears is even easier. They’re hanging out in online groups, chats, forums, and Slack channels sharing their frustrations and tips on how to get ahead.</p>

<p>Not only that but they’re having conversations in your community on channels you use every day. And both passive and active job hunters share a common trait.</p>

<p>They have FOMO (fear of missing out) when it comes to their peers and the competition. If their friends work for an inspiring startup that shares an incredible culture … they’re bound to want in.</p>

<h3 id="create-a-culture-of-inclusion-and-innovation">Create a culture of inclusion and innovation</h3>

<p>You can start a conversation with prospective talent by simply reaching out to see what they’re up to and nurturing a relationship. No strings attached means you can easily gather intel.</p>

<p>You’ll win friends and influence people by going off-script and avoiding buzzwords and bullet-points. Eventually sharing why your business culture and mission stand out is how so many startups succeed early on.</p>

<p>Setting out to build a culture that resonates with prospective employees should be a rung in your talent acquisition strategy. And it’s one of the most important reasons top talent will choose to work with you.</p>

<h3 id="93-of-employees-mention-company-culture-in-their-online-job-reviews">93% of employees <a href="https://www.glassdoor.com/employers/resources/hr-and-recruiting-stats/" target="_blank">mention company culture</a> in their online job reviews</h3>

<p>But how do you sell culture the old fashioned way? By establishing substance over style.</p>

<p>By differentiating your small business or agency from the soul-crushing ethos of big corporations. Only then can you can appeal to the hearts and minds of your new hires.</p>

<p>And by creating a unique culture, brand, and mission that feels like a “velvet rope” experience, you’ll have them lining up to get on the list.</p>

<h3 id="the-power-of-social-media-the-human-touch-and-referrals">The power of social media, the human touch, and referrals</h3>

<p>In this era of digital disruption, reputation management is critical. Branding your small business to emphasize culture on all channels boosts your time-to-hire and quality-of-hire.</p>

<p>And emphasizing the unique human touch of a small business to prospects is important. By showing that working for you will be a rewarding experience for growth and opportunity that isn’t mired in bureaucracy.</p>

<p>Setting up a referral program can give your hiring a shot in the arm too. Referrals most often come from your current employees. Colleagues recommending colleagues.</p>

<p>We’re big believers in the power of community and building teams based on word-of-mouth talent networks. You can attract some incredible people that way, we see it every day.</p>

<h3 id="non-traditional-compensation-packages-are-the-new-normal">Non-traditional compensation packages are the new normal</h3>

<p>The future of work is flexible. By selling your culture, and needed job flexibility, small businesses can win top talent.</p>

<p>As your business grows you can incentivize the experience by rewarding employees for referrals that make it past <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/10/21/an-80-point-employee-onboarding-checklist-for-long-term-success/" target="_blank">the critical six-month rubicon</a>.</p>

<p>And by offering new hires equity, a chance to be a part of a unique brand, and more growth opportunities, you can stand out from the big guys.</p>

<h3 id="every-job-opening-is-an-opportunity--feedback-ftw">Every job opening is an opportunity – Feedback FTW</h3>

<p>With every job opening comes great responsibility. Even with the standout job applicants, you don’t hire, you can nurture long-term relationships that can lead to future hires.</p>

<p>“Talents are 4x more likely to consider a company for a future opportunity when a company offers feedback.” — <a href="https://www.shrm.org/ResourcesAndTools/business-solutions/Documents/Talent-Acquisition-Report-All-Industries-All-FTEs.pdf" target="_blank">SHRM Customized Benchmarking Report</a></p>

<p>By nurturing future talent at every juncture you’re giving your small business or agency a great shot at delivering that one-of-a-kind work/life experience.</p>

<p>We love helping to empower small businesses with the talent sourcing to staff smarter. We’ve been sourcing a talent network of over 13,000 top tech professionals for over a decade.</p>

<p>There’s nothing more rewarding than helping inspiring brands build incredible teams. The future depends on it.</p>

<p>If you’re looking for help with your <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/09/how-digital-talent-sourcing-can-help-you-avoid-bad-hires/" title="Talent">talent sourcing strategy </a>drop us a line! Esteemed is dedicated to vetting and delivering quality tech talent when and where you need it.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kelton Reid</name></author><category term="Hiring Strategy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How can small businesses compete for top talent? Startups operating on a shoestring can still attract impactful teams. Here are some tips on how.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/alizee-baudez-sruzc3i_h8q-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/alizee-baudez-sruzc3i_h8q-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">An 80-Point Employee Onboarding Checklist for Long-term Success</title><link href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/10/21/an-80-point-employee-onboarding-checklist-for-long-term-success/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An 80-Point Employee Onboarding Checklist for Long-term Success" /><published>2020-10-21T13:56:31+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-21T13:56:31+00:00</updated><id>https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/10/21/an-80-point-employee-onboarding-checklist-for-long-term-success</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/10/21/an-80-point-employee-onboarding-checklist-for-long-term-success/"><![CDATA[<p>Whether you work with in-house, remote contractors, or fully-distributed teams, the way you onboard new employees is crucial to your long-term success.</p>

<p>By creating <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/09/how-digital-talent-sourcing-can-help-you-avoid-bad-hires/" target="_blank">a repeatable process for sourcing</a>, orienting, and assimilating new employees you’re giving your business the best chance for retention.</p>

<p>And it starts well before the day they begin their new gig. The onboarding process can start as soon as the ink dries on any agreement — and before — for your best outcome.</p>

<p>Many successful companies have begun to onboard potential employees before they even fill out an application. They reserve a portion of their website for orienting potential hires and to broadcast company culture.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Companies that excel at onboarding and employee retention experienced <a href="https://image-src.bcg.com/Images/BCG_From_Capability_to_Profitability_Jul_2012_tcm9-103684.pdf" target="_blank">2.5 times the revenue growth and 1.9 times the profit margin</a> of companies who struggle with these two critical skills.”</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="how-to-build-retention-from-the-inside-out">How to build retention from the inside-out</h3>

<p>We know the pain points so many businesses face <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/30/why-demand-for-tech-talent-is-so-high/" target="_blank">engaging and retaining top IT talent</a>. And for many tech pros, starting a new job has never been more stressful.</p>

<p>So we’ve put together a helpful list of some onboarding basics to help you get new hires where they need to be. And it’s built by setting them up for success in their first year.</p>

<p>The <strong>first six months</strong> are a proving ground for any employee. 30% of new hires will quit within six months of starting, and 16-17% within the first three (<a href="https://www.bamboohr.com/" target="_blank">BambooHR</a>).</p>

<p>Why do so many new employees leave so soon after starting? It’s not rocket science, in fact, they’re more likely to <a href="https://www.shrm.org/resourcesandtools/hr-topics/talent-acquisition/pages/onboarding-key-retaining-engaging-talent.aspx" target="_blank">tell you in online reviews</a> than ever:</p>

<ul>
  <li>23% will leave due to unclear guidelines around their new job</li>
  <li>21% because they feel they’ve received ineffective training</li>
  <li>17% due to a feeling of isolation or lack of social bonding</li>
  <li>12% because they feel their work goes unrecognized</li>
  <li>And 9% will leave because of a lack of feedback from superiors and co-workers</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-difference-between-quick-vs-long-term-onboarding">The difference between “quick” vs. long-term onboarding</h3>

<p>Building an effective and creative team of problem-solvers is expensive. So ensuring that your employees make it to that critical one year mark should be imperative.</p>

<p><strong>Onboarding process planning</strong> questions all companies can start with:</p>

<ol>
  <li>When will your onboarding begin for new employees?</li>
  <li>How long will it extend?</li>
  <li>What is the overall goal for new employees at the conclusion of the:</li>
  <li>First day …</li>
  <li>First week …</li>
  <li>First month …</li>
  <li>First three months …</li>
  <li>First six months …</li>
  <li>By the end of their first year?</li>
  <li>What will new employees need to know about your company culture, mission, and office set up – or remote processes – prior to starting?</li>
  <li>How does your HR team assist in the onboarding process? Managers? Co-workers?</li>
  <li>Will your organization create a dedicated onboarding team?</li>
  <li>Can you create social media content that promotes company culture?</li>
  <li>What about producing a video orienting new hires to the company culture showcasing success stories and more?</li>
  <li>Will you create an onboarding collaboration system — or kanban board — for tracking where employees are in the process?</li>
  <li>What milestones and long-term goals will need to be set for new hires?</li>
  <li>And how will you and your team measure the success of your onboarding KPIs moving ahead?</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="pre-onboarding-for-the-win">Pre-onboarding for the win</h3>

<p>One survey by <a href="https://www.aberdeen.com/research/" target="_blank">Aberdeen Group</a> showed that 83% of the most successful organizations begin onboarding before a new hire’s first day.</p>

<p>As soon as your new team member has accepted an offer the onboarding process can begin. Even before that critical first day — always a slog — you can get them into your funnel and on the path to a long career.</p>

<p><strong>Pre-onboarding</strong> suggestions to smoothly transition new hires:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Create a dedicated area on your website or Slack to welcome new employees and begin the process.</li>
  <li>Automate some of the tedious processes for new hires to help them speed up their assimilation and measure their progress.</li>
  <li>Have new employees e-sign docs gradually instead of having them piled on all at once.</li>
  <li>A friendly note and welcome kit from a new manager or the CEO can go a long way to acquainting them.</li>
  <li>New hire announcements and welcomes from co-workers also establish the kind of social onboarding that new employees need to feel invested.</li>
  <li>Ask them to interact with company social media accounts to promote connection.</li>
  <li>FAQs about the first day and a glossary of company terminology helps otherwise competent pros feel confident going into meetings full of unfamiliar internal jargon.</li>
  <li>An electronic handbook outlining a summary of job expectations and any boundaries around their new position can set them up for success right away.</li>
  <li>Point to suggested reading and success resources for additional fulfillment.</li>
  <li>Make sure they have all the tools they’ll need for a smooth and successful first day including:</li>
  <li>Having their new office or tech equipment — or remote setup — ready to roll, including software and operating systems.</li>
  <li>Passwords, logins, and any security access required to do all the things needed to interact with the team.</li>
  <li>A real or virtual coffee hour to get to know the team prior to diving into the nitty-gritty of the first day.</li>
  <li>Be sure to <a href="https://esteemed.io/blog/2020/09/21/creating-a-candidate-persona/" target="_blank">refer back to interviews to learn more</a> about your new employee’s soft skills, whether they are introverted or extroverted, and how to best incorporate those talents.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="expectations-at-the-outset-build-engagement">Expectations at the outset build engagement</h3>

<p>Accountability and small wins breed success. And giving your new team members all of the tools they need is a key to retention and attaining objectives.</p>

<p><strong>First-day checklist</strong> ideas:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Get team members set up with their new office or tech equipment.</li>
  <li>Establish emails, aliases, and access to online platforms needed to communicate effectively.</li>
  <li>Be sure to reiterate roles and responsibilities for not only new hires but the whole team.</li>
  <li>A company directory, map, and org. chart can acquaint them faster.</li>
  <li>Have them start the onboarding roadmap prepared for their first-week that outlines the goals and knowledge they’ll need to acquire.</li>
  <li>Invite employees to join the onboarding collaboration system — or kanban board — to see where they are in the process.</li>
  <li>Establish a training timeline and details they’ll need for any training sessions.</li>
  <li>Set expectations for what knowledge or testing to expect after training is completed.</li>
  <li>Set them up with a mentor or two who can help them along the onboarding journey.</li>
  <li>The importance of <strong>social onboarding</strong> and maintaining an ongoing relationship goes a long way to retention. Seeing a smile on a friendly face is always a bonus.</li>
  <li>Invite them to get to know their co-workers by asking them personal questions about their interests and pursuits outside of work.</li>
  <li>Plan a social interaction like a team lunch — or virtual meet up — for new hires on their first day to get to know them better.</li>
  <li>Have them get started on their initial assignments right away.</li>
  <li>Set them up for some early wins in the first few weeks so they feel confident in the first month.</li>
  <li>Promote inclusivity to help all newer employees feel socially connected to staff both old and new.</li>
  <li>Check-in with them to be sure they’re feeling confident and have all the tools required to do their job.</li>
  <li>Encourage over-communication and not to be shy about asking questions.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="confidence-builds-long-term-loyalty">Confidence builds long-term loyalty</h3>

<p>Companies most successful at onboarding saw 62% of their new hires meet their first performance milestone, and <a href="http://deliberatepractice.com.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Onboarding-2013.pdf" target="_blank">91% were still part of the team after their first year</a>.</p>

<p><strong>First-week onboarding</strong> ideas:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Be sure to re-emphasize new team member’s responsibilities and accountability for tasks in the weeks ahead.</li>
  <li>Clear goals + realistic expectations = Short term wins.</li>
  <li>Arrange daily one-on-one check-ins with either mentors or managers to establish consistent support.</li>
  <li>Get feedback — anonymously when possible — as to what they feel is or isn’t working in their first week.</li>
  <li>Continue to include new hires in company events, social gatherings, and ways to promote your business culture and diversity.</li>
  <li>Establish ongoing training updates, cross-training timelines, and details for any upcoming sessions.</li>
  <li>Set expectations for what knowledge or testing to expect after additional training is completed.</li>
  <li>Give ongoing reviews and establish high-level goals and deliverables for 3-6-9 month intervals. Wash, rinse, repeat.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="inclusion-empowerment-and-social-acceptance">Inclusion, empowerment, and social acceptance</h3>

<p>Success is built iteratively and each new team member will have their own concerns, feedback, needs, and hopes for their future with your organization. Taking the time to onboard over the first year will save you money in the long run.</p>

<p><strong>First-month onboarding</strong> ideas:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Establish a one-month check-in and informal review to ensure team members are finding the resources they need to succeed and hit benchmarks.</li>
  <li>Get more feedback — anonymously when possible — as to what they feel is or isn’t working.</li>
  <li>Check-in with their mentors to establish the effectiveness of training and guidance.</li>
  <li>Continue to encourage engagement in company events, social gatherings, and promotion of your business culture and diversity.</li>
  <li>Establish ongoing training updates, cross-training timelines, and details for any upcoming sessions.</li>
  <li>Set expectations for what knowledge or testing to expect after additional training is completed.</li>
  <li>Give ongoing reviews and establish high-level goals and deliverables for 3-6-9 month intervals.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="build-culture-community-and-ongoing-communication">Build culture, community, and ongoing communication</h3>

<p>After the first three months, your new team members should be well familiarized and entrenched in both your company culture and their new responsibilities.</p>

<p><strong>Three-month</strong> <strong>onboarding</strong> ideas:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Establish a three-month check-in and informal review to ensure team members are finding the resources they need to succeed and hitting benchmarks.</li>
  <li>Get more feedback — anonymously when possible — as to what they feel is or isn’t working.</li>
  <li>Check-in with their mentors to establish the effectiveness of guidance and <strong>finalize training</strong>.</li>
  <li>Continue to encourage engagement in company events, social gatherings, and promotion of your business culture and diversity.</li>
  <li>Give ongoing reviews and establish high-level goals and deliverables for 6-9 month intervals.</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Six-month</strong> <strong>onboarding</strong> ideas:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Establish a six-month check-in and <strong>performance review</strong>.</li>
  <li>Get more feedback — anonymously when possible — as to what they feel is or isn’t working.</li>
  <li>Check-in with their mentors to establish the effectiveness of guidance and set goals for the <strong>next two quarters</strong>.</li>
  <li>Confirm that employee has received <strong>all required training</strong>.</li>
  <li>Continue to encourage engagement in company events, social gatherings, and promotion of your business culture and diversity.</li>
  <li>Establish high-level goals and deliverables for the first year.</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>First-year</strong> <strong>review</strong>:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Perform a <strong>yearly performance review</strong> with your star employee.</li>
  <li>Be sure to broadcast their first successful year at the company.</li>
  <li>Discuss the hopes for the upcoming year’s projects, milestones, and KPIs.</li>
  <li>Address any feedback, questions, and needs your employees may have for the future.</li>
  <li>Review compensation and raise policies.</li>
  <li>Celebrate!</li>
</ol>

<p>Creating a standardized onboarding process gives you a statistical advantage for both retention and higher productivity.</p>

<p>With over ten years of helping clients find the right IT professionals for the job, we’ve seen the results speak for themselves. Onboarding the right way is an investment in your future.</p>

<p>If you need help finding the right team of qualified and talented tech professionals, drop us a line! We love helping businesses reach their goals.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kelton Reid</name></author><category term="Hiring Strategy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Where does the onboarding process start for new hires? Long before their first day if you want to keep them beyond those critical first six months!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/william-iven-gcsnospexfs-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://esteemed.io/uploads/william-iven-gcsnospexfs-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>